<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[This mater treateth of a merchauntes wyfe that afterwarde went like a man and was called Frederyke of Jennen.]</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1517</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11361A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109822</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845466</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845466</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10368</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01245)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10368)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 67:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[This mater treateth of a merchauntes wyfe that afterwarde went like a man and was called Frederyke of Jennen.]</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4+] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1517?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>A3r begins: How two.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A² ³.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; a fragment consisting of two leaves, the first of which is torn, with loss of print (title taken from STC 11361, of which this is another edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Male impersonators --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="fragmentary_text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10368:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10368:1"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How foure marchauntes met <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> whiche were of foure dyuerſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de all to Parys.</head>
               <p>IN the yere of our lorde <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> happened that four<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> out of dyuerſe country<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> as they were goyn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>une they met all togyder and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gyder / for they were all foure goynge <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Fraunce &amp; for company ſake they rode <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> unto one ynne / &amp; it was about ſhraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyde in the mooſt ioyfull tyme of all the yere and theyr na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes were called as here foloweth. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt was called Cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant of Spayne / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond was called Borchart of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / the thyrde was called Iohan of Flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; the fourth was called Ambroſe of Iennen. Than by the conſent of the other marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes Borcharde of fraunce went vnto the hoſte and ſayd. Hoſte now is the meryeſt tyme of the yere and we be foure marchauntes of foure dyuerſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes &amp; by fortune we met all togyder in one place &amp; out iorney is to Parys. And therfore whyle we be ſo met lette vs make good there togyder / &amp; ordeyne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt meet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye can get for money agaynſt to morowe and byd alſo ſome of your beſte frindes that you loue mooſte that we maye make good there togyder or that we deparſe fro henſe / and we ſhall co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tente you all your money agayne. And than the hoſte ſayde that he wolde do it with a good wyll and than went he and bad many of his good frendes and neyghbours to dyner and he bought of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt meet that he coude get for money and brought it home. And on the morowe he dreſſed it and made it redy agaynſt dyner af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the beſt maner y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he coude. And whan y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was dyner
<pb facs="tcp:10368:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> geſtes to dyner &amp; the marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> them welcome. Than bad y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at he ſholde brynge in the meete &amp; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> myght go to dyner. And than the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>yll. Than went the hoſte and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> meet &amp; ſet it theron &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtes to them &amp; ſyt dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> good chere al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daye longe with good honeste<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as very late with daunſynge &amp; lepynge. And <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad done / the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes toke theyr leue of the marcha<gap reason="illegible" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; thanked them for theyr good chere. And than euery man departed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to his houſe. And than cam the marchauntes to the hoſte &amp; prayed hym hertely for to come in &amp; thanked hym that he had ordered &amp; done all thynges ſo well and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly.</p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10368:2"/>
               <head>¶ How two of the marchauntes / as Iohan <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Ambroſius of Iennen hyld one another, v. thou<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> golde guldens.</head>
               <p>wHan al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; the geſtes had m<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye togyder al the daye longe / at nyght t<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> toke theyr leue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked them for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good chere that they had made them / &amp; ſo departed euery one to theyr lodgynge. And whan that they were depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted euery man to theyr houſe / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wexed it late. And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cam the hoſte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe to the marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; aſked them yf that they wolde go ſlepe / &amp; they anſwered vnto theyr hoſte yes. And than toke he a candel and brought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes into a fayre chambre / where was. iiij. beddes rychely hanged with coſtely curtaynes that euerye mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt myght lye by themſelfe. And whan that they we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re all togyder in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chamber / than began they to ſpeke of many thynges / ſome good / ſome bad as it laye in theyr myndes. Than ſayd Courant of ſpayne. Syrs we haue be all this daye mery and made good chere &amp; euerye one of vs hath a fayre wyfe at home: howe fare they nowe at home we can not tel. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd bourcharde of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the other marchauntes. What aſke you how they do<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> They ſyt by the fyere and make good chere and eate / &amp; drynke of the beſte and laboure not at all / &amp; ſo get they vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to them hote blode &amp; than they maye take an other luſty yonge man and do theyr pleaſure with hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we knowe not of / for we be oftentymes long from them &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lenne a lofe for a nede ſecretly to an other. Than ſayd Iohan of Florence / we may all well be called fooles &amp; nydeates that truſte our wyfes in this maner as we do: for a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hert is not made of ſo hard a ſtone but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10368:3"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wyll melte / for a womans nature is to be vnſtedfaſte and tourneth as the wynde dothe and careth not for vs tyll the tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we come agayne. And we labour dayely bothe in wynde and rayne and put often our lyues in to pardy and in auenture on the ſee for to fynd them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>all &amp; ou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wyfes ſyt at home and make good chere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other good felowes &amp; gyue them parte of the money that we get. And therfore an ye wyll do after my counſayle / let euery one of vs take a fayre wenche to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>al as well as our wyfes do / &amp; they ſhall knowe no more of that / than we knowe of them. Than ſayde Ambroſius of Ienne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them. By goddes grace that ſhall I neuer do whyle y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I lyue. For I haue at home a good &amp; a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous woman and a womanlye. And I know<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe is not of that dyſpoſycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe wyl eſchewe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of all ſuche yll abuſyons tyl the tyme that I com home agayn. For I knowe well that ſhe wyl haue non other man but me alone. And yf that I ſhold breke my wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke than were I but lytell worthe. Than ſayd Iohn of Florence. Felowe ye ſet moche pryce by your wyfe at home and truſte her with all that ye haue I wyll laye with you a wager of. v. thouſande guldens yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wyl abyde me here I ſhal departe &amp; ryde to Iennen &amp; do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your wyfe my wyll. Than ſayd Ambroſius to Iohan of Florenſe. I haue delyuered to my hoſte. v. thouſand guldens to kepe / put ye downe as moche agaynſte it &amp; I ſhal tarye here tyll the tyme that ye retourne agayn from Ie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nen / &amp; yf that you by ony maner of menes can get your pleaſure of my wyfe ye ſhall haue all this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Than ſayd Iohan of Florence. I am content / and than putted he in his hoſtes hande other. v. thouſande guldens agaynſte Ambroſes money. And than toke he<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:10368:3"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
